{
  "reference_number": "9421",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "Setting a firm target creates greater certainty and a more stable environment in which investment decisions can be made, early on.\n By encouraging the required investment into infrastructure at the outset there will be a stronger probability that 2050 targets will be\n\n met."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Managing emissions reduction requires long-term behaviour change. Reducing all greenhouse gas emissions from across all sectors\n – including the agricultural sector - requires that technologies and new methodologies be introduced early on to combat the long-\n\n term effects of global warming resulting from greenhouse gas emissions. Clear policy signals and firm targets will stimulate\n investment into low emission agricultural techniques, ensuring that NZ is able to be more resilient in terms of managing its cross-\n sector emissions; managing and preserving its immediate natural environment; and building long-term export market resilience by\n\n maintaining a competitive edge in international markets."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Relying on domestic carbon sinks and abatement technologies will greatly improve both New Zealand’s cyclical carbon sequestration\n capacity and support native biodiversity through substantially increased native forest coverage. This is preferable to transferring\n emission abatement obligations overseas through the purchase of potentially sub-standard credits. Internalising domestic emissions\n\n reductions will also stimulate investment into research and development of cleaner technologies, practices and abatement methods."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The only scenario in which an adjustment might be considered necessary is one that demands an even more stringent target to be\n set (i.e. a target set against a baseline earlier than 1990)."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Five-year cycles provide achievable short-term goals that will enable New Zealand to stay on track for meeting its 2050 target."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "Setting firm budgets signals stability and certainty to investors. The likely knock-on effect would be a stimulation of local investment in\nclean tech and a stimulation of inflows of foreign direct investment into New Zealand as a hub for clean tech innovation. By contrast,\n\non-going adjustments to any given carbon budget should only be done so in the context of where targets are being exceeded or\noutperformed i.e. if New Zealand’s emissions abatement trajectory is on a steeper downward curve than originally estimated, the\n\nbudgets may be adjusted to reflect that, and in doing so support sustained, strong performance."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Unless New Zealand is outperforming its targets, in which case the budgets should be revised to sustain forward momentum."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Four key issues to consider are: 1. Decarbonising buildings: Adjusting current building standards and codes to support future carbon\n\ntargets. A focus on the following areas could deliver positive carbon reduction outcomes: a) All new building stock be mandated to\nadhere to green building codes and meet sustainability criteria. The minimum mandatory requirement be at least Home Star 6, in\n\nterms of energy efficiency. Future-proofing new builds should be a primary consideration in terms of capturing the potential for low\ncarbon emission energy generation and storage (i.e. solar conduit battery use and electric vehicle charging capacity in all new builds).\nb) The existing housing stock of 1.8 million homes - 800,000 of which are currently not adequately insulated - represents a significant\n\nopportunity and challenge in terms of reducing emissions, with particular regard to Government’s recent legislation relating to\nmandatory heating requirements. These new mandates, coupled with a potential shortage of affordable insulation and energy\n\nefficient heating appliances, suggests that energy-related emissions may be exacerbated by an initial supply shock (where demand\noutstrips supply). Government should therefore consider whether the existing policy framework is fit-for-purpose in terms of\n\ntransitioning to a low carbon economy and whether New Zealand be looking to other frameworks i.e. that of the UK where energy\nrating systems have been introduced, and where subsidies and tax reliefs are leveraged to stimulate investment into and market\ngrowth of insulation and energy efficiency products. c) In view of the forthcoming Building Code review, building standards such as H1\n\nEnergy Efficiency Standard (NZS 421:2009), should be reviewed with the objective of mandating minimum standards that deliver\ncarbon savings through energy efficient buildings. The current requirements are currently inadequate and should be tightened. d)\n\nIntroducing a Home Star minimum standard for existing homes – rental homes in particular, as a means of improving the energy\nefficiency of existing building stock, while simultaneously addressing social and environmental equity issues, given that rentals tend\n\nto be maintained to a lower standard than owner occupied homes. 2. Renewables and clean tech: Leveraging appropriate policy tools\nto support Governments long-term carbon reduction target through renewable energy generation and Electric Vehicle (EV) charging\n\ninfrastructure. For example, manage the anticipated largescale uptake of EVs and associated energy demand management,\nsubsidies and taxes could be leveraged by: - creating an environment conducive to fast-tracking much needed investment in EV\ncharging infrastructure and incentivising the uptake of EVs in the mainstream / middle / low income market through making 2nd hand\n\nEVs as affordable as 2nd hand internal combustion engine vehicles. - supporting the build out of distributed energy with energy\nstorage, and/or district heating and cooling (with storage) - sidestepping a potential demand crunch on existing energy sources,\n\ntransmission and grid infrastructure. - increasing low carbon utility-scale renewable energy generation (i.e. fast tracking consented\nutility-scale onshore and offshore wind and ground mounted solar arrays, hydro energy and more). Encourage investment into\n\ninfrastructure that supports nascent technologies such as - hydrogen fuel cells Domestic food security: Transport emissions\nassociated with increased food imports will negatively weight the carbon budget. A recent report from HortNZ indicates that on the\ncurrent population growth trajectory, demand will outstrip future supply of domestic production by 2020. Domestic food supply is\n\npivotal to carbon targets being met, given that food represents the greatest portion of consumption emissions (32% of Auckland’s\nhousehold emissions according to the 2014 report by Motu Economic Research– Greenhouse Gas Emissions New Zealand: A\n\npreliminary Consumption-based analysis (Romanos, Kerr and Will); and food and restaurants accounting for 30% of Auckland’s per\ncapita consumption emissions according to C40 Cities consumption emissions data report 2018. Careful assessment of land\n\nallocation for housing development is urgently required to ensure that prime growing land is protected from housing development;\nthat domestic supply of vegetables can meet demand; and that climate change and carbon reduction is embedded in land-use and\n\nplanning policy. 4. Public transport infrastructure: Transport accounts for the second-largest share of emissions from households\n(27% - Motu Economic and Public Policy Research) and individuals (23% - C40 Cities Consumption emissions calculation). Ensuring\nthat adequate investment is allocated to public transport infrastructure, particularly in new, high growth areas such as South and\n\nNorth Auckland, is key to reducing per capita carbon emissions. Plans tabled by Greater Auckland (congestion free network and\nRegional Rapid Rail) merit consideration. High deprivation urban areas should also be prioritised and supported with affordable lower\n\ncarbon transport options, to ensure that equity issues arising from fuel taxes, for example, are addressed. In terms of key\nstakeholders that the government should be working with: If New Zealand does follow the UK Climate Change Act model, it follows\n\nthat the NZ Climate Change Act would result in a legal requirement for ALL government departments to be responsible for reducing\nand reporting emissions from their own buildings and estate, and for assessing the carbon impact of new policies. Strategic partners\nwould include: • The government departments most likely to lead on emissions reductions (transport, energy, agriculture/primary\n\nindustries, built environment). • All Public Service Departments, Non-Public Service Departments, Crown Entities (Crown Agents,\nAutonomous Crown Entities, Independent Crown Entities) and Crown Entity Companies (Crown Research Institutes and Other\n\nCompanies). • School Boards of Trustees and Tertiary Education Institutes, Public Finance Act Schedule 4 Organisations, Reserve\nBank of New Zealand, State-Owned Enterprises and Mixed Ownership Model companies. • Community groups. Behaviour change is\n\npivotal to New Zealand meeting its carbon targets, in terms of reducing household carbon emissions. Communities should be\nactively engaged, educated, encouraged and incentivised to prioritise energy efficiency, sustainable travel and low carbon\nconsumption habits. • Large and medium-sized businesses are also key partners, with regard to their influence in shaping consumer\n\nbehaviour and related environmental outcomes. • Local Boards, councils and community groups hold valuable knowledge in terms of\nmaterial opportunities in any given area and holding valuable insight into effective community engagement methods; and effective\n\nprogramme deployment. These organisations represent the interests of communities, business, NFP and NGOs across New Zealand,\nall of whom will play a vital role in leading the cultural change and behaviour change required to move New Zealand to zero emissions\n\nfuture."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "As informed experts the Climate Change Commission should have a highly influential voice in goal setting."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "The Climate Change Commission will be comprised of New Zealand’s leading minds/sector/subject matter experts. It will be well-\ninformed to take such decisions, as an independent body."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The balance of expertise within the Climate Change Commission may be further improved if business expertise was added to the mix;\nthe result being a Climate Change Commission that is more representative and informed - to the extent that it can set reliable targets\n\nindependent of government. Private sector representation could potentially be included on a rotational basis, to improve\naccountability and avoid the risk of perceived bias."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, in terms of ensuring that risks are well understood and that the policy framework in place addresses such risks and enables\ndecisive action to be taken to diminish, mitigate or pre-empt risks."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Mandated reporting requirements will serve to improve transparency and will assist organisations and Government in more effective\nrisk management."
    }
  ]
}
